Guide to the Dwight Macdonald Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Dwight Macdonald papers
1865-1984
1920-1978
MS 730
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
94.25
The papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts, notes, printed material, photographs, audiotapes, and memorabilia documenting the personal life and professional career of Dwight Macdonald. Macdonald's literary career, political activities, teaching and speaking engagements, and personal life are detailed. Major subjects represented in the papers include: communism and the Trotskyite movement, journalism and publishing, American social and political life (1920s-1970s), pacifism, and the Congress for Cultural Freedom. Correspondence files include letters with many prominent intellectual and political figures.
Macdonald, Dwight, 1906-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Dwight Macdonald, 1974-1978; and Mrs. Macdonald, 1984-1985. Gift of Leonard Vanderpot, 2009.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series and two additions: I. Correspondence. II. Research and Writing. III. Teaching and Lectures. IV. Trotskyist Movement. V. politics Magazine. VI. Miscellany. 1984 July Addition. 1985 November Addition.
Scope and Contents
The Dwight Macdonald Papers consist of seventy-three feet of correspondence, manuscripts, notes, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia extending mainly from 1920 to 1978. They constitute a remarkably large fraction of the biographically and historically important papers that can ever have passed through Macdonald's hands. Almost all major aspects of his personal and public life are well documented except that there are very few items related to his work on the editorial staffs of Fortune and Partisan Review. Many other prominent intellectuals are represented by rich and voluminous correspondence. The papers also contain valuable material for studies of these subjects among many others: Exeter and Yale in the 1920s; Communism and the Trotskyist movement in the 1930s and 1940s; little magazines in the same period; American assistance to refugees from Franco's Spain; international pacifist sentiment during and after World War II; the Congress for Cultural Freedom; opposition to the war in Vietnam; film criticism; and interpretation of mass culture.
The Dwight Macdonald Papers are arranged in six series:
I Correspondence
II Research and Writing
III Teaching and Lectures
IV Trotskyist Movement
V politics Magazine
VI Miscellany
Series I, Correspondence, has two sections: Family and General. The Family correspondence consists of letters that Macdonald exchanged with his close relations--principally his parents, brother, wives, and sons--and letters that they exchanged with other persons. Researchers seeking an extended private view of Macdonald's life should also examine his correspondence with Exeter classmate Dinsmore Wheeler in the General section.
The General section contains all non-family correspondence in the papers with these partial exceptions: routine editorial exchanges and reader response to books and articles (Series II); correspondence related to academic appointments (Series III); letters related to the Trotskyist movement (Series IV) and the editing and publication of politics (Series V); and miscellaneous correspondence connected with personal business and the literary executorship of the Delmore Schwartz estate (Series VI). The folder listing for this section has cross-references to incoming letters in the later series that have an interest independent of Macdonald's role in the activities documented in those series. Correspondence related to certain special subjects--"The Camacho Letter," "The Encounter Row," "The Franco Letter," "Mission to Moscow," and "The Nation Letter," among others--has been kept together as Macdonald left it. Persons whose letters are filed under these headings are listed under their own names with appropriate cross-references.
The correspondence in the General section has much to offer the historian or biographer whose interest is in American and European intellectual life between the 1920s and the 1970s. The letters are full of important ideas and observations, and there are many extended arguments between Macdonald and his correspondents that show them developing and refining their positions in the course of controversy.
It would require several pages to list all of Macdonald's correspondents who have contributed importantly to twentieth-century intellectual and cultural life, but these are some of the leading thinkers and writers with whom he has exchanged numerous or important letters: Daniel Aaron, Lionel Abel, James Agee, Sherwood Anderson, Hannah Arendt, W.H. Auden, Daniel Bell, Peter Blake, William F. Buckley, Jr., Nicola Chiaromonte, Helen Constas, Dorothy Day, John Dos Passos, F.W. Dupee, T.S. Eliot, James T. Farrell, Waldo Frank, Nathan Glazer, Paul Goodman, Esther Dette Hamill, Elizabeth Hardwick, Geoffrey T. Hellman, Will Herberg, Irving Howe, Jane Jacobs, John K. Jessup, Alfred Kazin, Irving Kristol, Melvin Lasky, Mary McCarthy, Norman Mailer, Ralph Manheim, George L.K. Morris, George Orwell, William Phillips, Ezra Pound, Philip Rahv, Kenneth Rexroth, David Riesman, Diego Rivera, Bertrand Russell, Delmore Schwartz, William Shawn, Stephen Spender, Carlo Tresca, Diana Trilling, Lionel Trilling, Leon Trotsky, Niccolo Tucci, Peter Viereck, Edmund Wilson, Richard Wollheim, and George Woodcock.
Macdonald's correspondence with many lesser-known individuals is also of considerable value. In his Trotskyist period he exchanged letters with Max Shachtman, James P. Cannon, and other members of the Socialist Workers Party. His pacifists stance in the politics period brought him in touch with GIs and civilians who shared his ideas. He heard about wartime Germany from Fritz T. Kaeser and Melvin Lasky and about postwar Germany and France from Emil Henk, Helmut Hirsch, and Mario Levi. His extensive correspondence with such European radicals as Victor Serge, Jean and Andrée Delecourt, and Jean Malaquais provides information about politics and culture in postwar Europe.
In his capacities as editor, critic, and friend, Macdonald received unpublished writings from many authors. These are among the most prominent writers who are represented in Series I by manuscripts as well as correspondence: James Agee, Peter Blake, Nicola Chiaromonte, Anton Ciliga, Eldridge Cleaver, Helen Constas, Jean and Andrée Delecourt, James T. Farrell, Ernst Federn, Hans Gerth, Morgan Gibson, Joseph Gould, Lawrence Grauman, Jr., Henry Hellman, Georges Henein, Sander Katz, Hans Kohn, Karl Korsch, Lucien Laurat, Eric Lee, Gershon Legman, Mario Levi, Robert Jay Lifton, John A. Lukacs, David McDowell, Norman Mailer, Ralph Manheim, Durham Miller, Sibyl Moholy-Nagy, Leo Moulin, A.J. Muste, Justin O'Brien, George Orwell, Henry M. Paechter, Kenneth Patchen, Dachine Rainer, John Crowe Ransom, Wilhelm Reich, Charles Rembar, Kenneth Rexroth, Diego Rivera, Ray McLeod Robinson, Selden Rodman, Maximilien Rubel, Derek S. Savage, Delmore Schwartz, Victor Serge, Wilfrid Sheed, Stephen Spender, Leon Trotsky, Niccolo Tucci, Peter Viereck, and John B. Wheelwright. Other manuscripts on political subjects are listed by author and title in Series IV and V.
Series II, Research and Writing, has four sections: Early Writings, Books and Pamphlets, Shorter Writings, and Subject File.
Early Writings consists mainly of notes, themes, and student publications, most of which Macdonald wrote at Exeter and Yale.
Books and Pamphlets and Shorter Writings consist of research material, notes, drafts, proofs, publications, editorial correspondence, reader response, and requests for reprint rights related to Macdonald's books, pamphlets, articles, and certain unpublished writings. Letters to the editor, both published and unpublished, have been filed in Series I, General, except when there were bulky notes, drafts, or research material. Other published and unpublished writings can be found in the other sections of this series and in Series III, IV, and V.
The Subject File consists of notes, research material, and drafts arranged by subject. The two largest groupings are research material and drafts related to Macdonald's unfinished book on United States Steel and the miscellaneous papers related to his writings on mass culture. The research material in this section includes important mimeographed and printed matter on these subjects among others: anarchism, pacifism, civil liberties, urban renewal in New York City, the war in Vietnam, and the New Left.
Series III, Teaching and Lectures, consists of notes, drafts, administrative records, correspondence, and student essays related to Macdonald's academic appointments and occasional lectures. Tapes of Macdonald's lectures at the University of Texas have been transferred to Historical Sound Recordings in Sterling Memorial Library. These are listed in an appendix.
Series IV, Trotskyist Movement, is a consolidation of much of the important political material in the papers. Among the major items are these: Macdonald's bibliography and notes on the movement, his writings for The New International, correspondence and mimeographed material documenting the split between the Socialist Workers Party and the Workers Party, and miscellaneous correspondence. Other important correspondence is filed under these names in Series I, General: Albert Goldman, Philip Gray, Freda Kirchwey, Felix Morrow, Max Shachtman, The Socialist Appeal, the Socialist Workers Party, and Leon Trotsky.
Series V, politics Magazine, consists of notes by Dwight Macdonald; published and unpublished manuscripts by Macdonald and others; correspondence with readers and contributors; proofs, dummies, and published copies of the magazine; financial records; and promotional matter. These papers are valuable for studying the business as well as the editorial aspect of publication; they provide much insight into the financial problems of a little magazine. Much of the correspondence with contributors and readers is in Series I, General, under these names among others: Lionel Abel, Bruno Bettelheim, Dorothy Brumm, Andrea Caffi, Nicola Chiaromonte, Lewis A. Coser, H.V. Crehan, Robert Dahl, Joel Dirlam, George P. Elliott, Jon Evans, Henry Geiger, Ethel Goldwater, Paul Goodman, Bertha Gruner, Zellig Harris, W.B. Hesseltine, Milton R. Konvitz, Karl Korsch, Melvin J. Lasky, Norman Matson, Judith Miller, C. Wright Mills, Norman Mini, George Orwell, William Petersan, Daniel Rosenblatt, Porter Sargent, Daniel Seligman, Victor Serge, Julian Symons, Niccolo Tucci, and George Woodcock.
Series VI, Miscellany, has six sections: Personal, Family, Photographs, Schwartz Estate, Legal and Financial, and Travel.
The Personal section consists of memorabilia, address and date books, clippings, and a few personal writings.
The Family section consists of miscellaneous papers created by or related to Macdonald's parents and children.
The Photographs section has snapshots and portraits of Dwight Macdonald, his family, and his friends.
The Schwartz Estate section consists of correspondence, notes, and drafts related to Macdonald's literary executorship of the Delmore Schwartz estate.
The Legal and Financial section consists of divorce agreements, wills and related correspondence, letters about the schooling of Michael and Nicholas G. Macdonald, and miscellaneous financial papers.
The Travel section consists of memorabilia related to Macdonald's travels, mainly in Western Europe, between 1933 and 1968.
Seven cartons of pamphlets, serials, newspapers, books, and government documents were separated from the papers for distribution to other parts of the Library's collections. Some of the pamphlets, mainly political publications from the 1930s and 1940s, have been incorporated in the Pamphlet Collection in this department. A list of selected titles is appended to this register. The serials, consisting mainly of political and literary magazines published in the 1930s and 1940s, included several copies of each of these titles: Chimera, Dialectics, East and West, Fact, Hound & Horn, International Review, Living Marxism, Modern Monthly, Pacifica, and Townsman. There were also copies of The Dial and The Little Review, published between 1923 and 1925, and of Eros and The Realist, published between 1961 and 1964, and single numbers of many other magazines. The newspapers consisted of American underground publications from the late 1960s and a file of the Indian paper Harijan for 1946 and 1947. The government documents were mainly federal publications on economic subjects.
The Dwight Macdonald Papers were purchased from Dwight Macdonald in 1975 and 1978.
Biographical / Historical
Dwight Macdonald (1906-1992)
Dwight Macdonald was for almost fifty years a productive and influential critic of politics, society, and culture in the United States and abroad. He is especially well-known for his writing on film, mass culture, and political ideas, but few subjects of humanistic interest have altogether escaped his attention. At different times he wrote regularly for Fortune, Partisan Review, The New International, politics (which he also edited and published), The New Yorker, Encounter, and Esquire, and his articles appeared occasionally in dozens of other periodicals. Among his longer works are The Root Is Man, "Masscult and Midcult," several volumes of essays, studies of Henry Wallace and the Ford Foundation, editions of Edgar Allan Poe and Alexander Herzen, and an anthology of parodies. He was also an important member and critic of a number of political movements and organizations, ranging in time from the Socialist Workers Party in the late 1930s to the anti-war movement in the late 1960s. From 1948 onward, he also lectured and taught courses on film, mass culture, politics, and other subjects in colleges and universities.
An education at Phillips Exeter Academy and Yale (B.A., 1928) provided Macdonald with a strong background in classical literature and reinforced his tendency to rely on his own taste and knowledge as his final measures of value. This self-assurance and skepticism shaped both his early approach to radical politics and his later ventures in cultural criticism. Experiences at Yale, in particular, foreshadowed the characteristic Macdonald protest: in a 1925 letter to President James R. Angell, he argued against compulsory chapel on the ground that the sermons offended his intelligence.
In the 1930s, along with many other disenchanted American intellectuals, Dwight Macdonald read Marx and turned to communism. In 1934 he wrote that he believed it to be the "only way out of the mess our society is in. Whether it's a blind alley is another question but it's the only alley that has any chance of not turning out to be blind." But unlike the majority of those who took this path, he affiliated himself with the Trotskyists rather than the Communists. A leading intellectual in the Socialist Workers Party from 1939 to 1941, he left the Party in the later year because of its lack of internal democracy and intellectual freedom.
Macdonald argued with the Trotskyists over organization and not ideology, but by the time he published "The Root Is Man" in 1946, he had completed an ideological break as well. Applying a single measure to politics and culture, he criticized either when it offended his intellect or the principles of his conservatism. Later in the 1940s, when he reflected on his involvement with the Trotskyists, he described the experience with a metaphor that recalled Exeter and Yale: "It really is like the old school tie, this having once been part of the Bolshevist Movement, and no matter how much one's reason and ethical values tell you now otherwise, one still has a sense that one 'belongs to the club.'"
During the politics period (1944-1949), Macdonald made a transition from socialist politics and literary criticism to anarchism, pacifism, and a broader critique of American culture. This period prepared him for the articles he would write in the 1950s and 1960s for Esquire and The New Yorker essays that retained his earlier concern for social reform and human welfare but defined culture in more elitist terms. He saw the job of a critic as more than reviewing or providing a consumer report on culture. Rather, he would insist on principles and standards; he would evaluate according to his taste and knowledge. He would undertake to distinguish between true culture and the insidious pseudo-culture ("mid-cult") of the Book-of-the-Month Club, the Great Books, and The Saturday Review.
Macdonald carried on his defense of principles and morality in culture by insisting on standards of taste and usage in language. Believing that language determines and reflects the strength and level of culture, he sought a balance between style and content. If, as he wrote in 1960, "Great ideas can only be expressed in a great style,"* content and style might serve as mutual upholders of culture. Radical politics (content) and conservative culture (standards of style and taste) coexisted for him in the medium of language.
Macdonald's left-handed attack on American politics and his right-handed critique of American culture have earned him the reputation of being "against" everything and not "for" anything. By way of this distinction, he further aided the cause of precision in language in an indirect way. A new term, descriptive of his type of criticism, bears his name: macdonaldize, meaning to find fault, or carp.
Macdonald died on December 19, 1982, in New York City.
These are among the principal events in Dwight Macdonald's personal and public life:
1906 Born on March 24 in New York City to Dwight Macdonald, Sr., and Alice Eliza Hedges Macdonald
[1916?]-1920 Attended the Barnard School
1920-1924 Attended Phillips Exeter Academy
1924-1928 Attended Yale College
1926 Death of Dwight Macdonald, Sr.
1927-1928 Served as Chairman of the Board of the Yale Record
1928 Spent six months with Macy's Executive Training Squad
1929 Met James Agee; became Associate Editor of Henry Luce's new magazine, Fortune
1930 Published six numbers of a literary magazine, The Miscellany, with Yale classmates George L.K. Morris, Geoffrey Hellman, and Frederick W. Dupee; films replaced literary criticism as his chief cultural interest
1934 Married Nancy Rodman
1936 Resigned from Fortune in dispute over editing of his articles criticizing United States Steel
1937 Became an editor of Partisan Review; published a three-part article on the Luce magazines in The Nation; wrote a letter to The Nation protesting its coverage of the American Writers Congress
1938 Birth of a son, Michael Dwight; began writing for The New International; wrote Fascism and the American Scene
1939 Joined the Trotskyist Party (Socialist Workers Party); became Acting Secretary of the League for Cultural Freedom and Socialism and signed its cable to French President Daladier protesting the imprisonment of French pacifists
1940 Wrote Jobs, Not Battleships for the Socialist Workers Party; sided with Max Shachtman's Workers Party in its split with James P. Cannon's SWP
1941 Resigned from the Workers Party over issues of intellectual freedom and party organization
1943 Resigned from the editorial board of Partisan Review, protesting a shift in emphasis from political to literary content
1944 Began publishing politics; wrote "A Theory of Popular Culture"; birth of second son, Nicholas Gardiner
1946 Wrote "The Root Is Man" for politics
1948 Publication of Henry Wallace: The Man and the Myth
1949 Discontinued publication of politics, giving as his reason a "stale, tired, disheartened, and... demoralized" feeling
1951 Joined the staff of The New Yorker
1953 Publication of The Root Is Man; publication of "The Bible in Modern Undress" in The New Yorker
1954 Divorced from Nancy Rodman Macdonald; married Gloria Lanier
1955 Publication of The Ford Foundation: The Men and the Millions
1956 Lived for a year in London as staff writer for Encounter; publication of Memoirs of a Revolutionist
1957 Death of Alice Hedges Macdonald
1958 "The Encounter Row," in which Dwight Macdonald charged that the Congress for Cultural Freedom wielded extensive editorial control; publication of "America! America!" in Dissent
1960 Publication of "Masscult and Midcult" in Partisan Review; became film critic for Esquire; publication of Parodies: An Anthology from Chaucer to Beerbohm---and After
1962 Publication of Against the American Grain
1963 Publication of "Our Invisible Poor" in The New Yorker
1964 Publication of "Fellini's Masterpiece" in Esquire
1965 Publication of Selected Poems of Edgar Allan Poe; left the staff of The New Yorker
1966 Dropped the Esquire film column
1967-1968 Wrote a political column for Esquire
1968 Publication of My Past and Thoughts: The Memoirs of Alexander Herzen
1969 Publication of Dwight Macdonald on Movies
1970 Reissue of Memoirs of a Revolutionist as Politics Past
1974 Publication of Discriminations
Appendix: Separated Materials
Political Pamphlets
These political pamphlets were separated from the Dwight Macdonald Papers and incorporated in the Pamphlet Collection in Manuscripts and Archives or transferred to other departments of Yale University Library:
Adler, Friedrich. The Witchcraft Trial in Moscow. New York,1937.
Adoratsky, V. The History of the Communist Manifesto of Marx and Engels. New York, 1938.
Aldred, Guy A. Bakunin. Glasgow, 1940.
____. Bakunin's Writings. Bombay, [1947].
Allen, Charles R. Concentration Camps, U.S.A. New York, [1952].
Allen, Rev. E. L. Pacifism as an Individual Duty. Oxford, 1946.
American Civil Liberties Union. Conscience and the War. New York, 1943.
____. Day of Protest, Night of Violence. Los Angeles, 1967.
____. Violence in Peekskill. New York, 1949.
American Friend Service Committee. Speak Truth to Power. Austin, Texas, 1955.
Baldwin, John Henry. How to Win the Masses. New York, 1944.
Beer, Max. A Guide to the Study of Marx. London, n.d.
Berlin, Isaiah. Two Concepts of Liberty. London, 1958.
Berneri, C. Peter Kropotkin. London, 1943.
Berneri, M. L. Workers in Stalin's Russia. London, 1944.
Bishop, Reg. Soviet Millionaires. London, 1945.
The Bourgeois Role of Bolshevism. Glasgow, n.d.
Browder, Earl. Traitors in American History. New York, 1938.
Brown, Oliver. Arms and the Men. Glasgow, [1942].
Cachin, Marcel. Preparation for War against the Soviet Union. Moscow, 1931.
Camus, Albert. Neither Victims Nor Executioners. Berkeley,1968.
The Case of Henryk Erlich and Victor Alter. London, 1943.
Chamber of Commerce of The United States. Communist Infiltration in the United States. Washington, D.C., 1946.
Ciliga, Anton. L'insurrection de Cronstadt. Lyon, n.d.
____. The Kronstadt Revolt. London, n.d.
Committee For Promotion of Peace. Falsifiers of History. New York, 1948.
Communist League of America. War and the 4th International. New York, 1934.
Congress of Racial Equality. Cracking the Color Line. New York, [1960?].
Constitution (Fundamental Law) of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. Moscow, 1947.
Constitution of the U.S.S.R. New York, 1947.
Critics Group. Dialectics. New York, 1937.
Darcy, Sam. An Eye-Witness of the Wrecker's Trial. New York, 1937.
Debs, Eugene V. Debs And the War. Chicago, [1926?].
Declaration of Principles and Constitution of the Socialist Workers Party. Chicago, 1938.
De Leon, Daniel. Revolutionary Socialism in U.S. Congress. New York, 1931.
Socialist Reconstruction of Society. New York, 1944.
Deutsch, Julius. The Civil War In Austria. Chicago, 1934.
Dewey, John. Truth is on the March. New York, 1937.
Ehrlich, Heinrich. The Struggle for Revolutionary Socialism. New York, 1934.
Finland Reveals Her Secret Documents. New York, 1941.
Fischer, Ernst. Trotsky Unmasked. New York, 1937.
Gandhi, M. K. The Doctrine of the Sword: The Law of Suffering Modern Politics. England, n.d.